Hi Good morning.
各位 早上好
It's wonderful to be back here.
很高兴能回到这里
Wonderful to see you here.
很高兴见到你们
I'm teaching this class
我教授这门课是因为
because I wish a class like this had been taught
在我读本科阶段时
when I was sitting in your seat as an undergrad here.
非常希望能学习这样一门课程
This does not mean it is a class you wish to be taught,
可能这门课并不是你希望的那样
nor does it mean that it is the right class for you.
也可能并不适合你
But I hope to doing the next couple of lectures is giving you an idea what this class is about
但希望几堂课后 你能有个大概印象
so that you can decide whether or not it is for you.
让你决定这门课是否适合你
I came here in 1992
我1992年来到哈佛求学
一开始主修计算机科学
And then I had a mini epiphany half way through my sophomore year.
大二期间 突然顿悟了
I realized that I was in a wonderful place
我意识到我身处让人神往大学校园
with wonderful students around me, wonderful teachers.
周围都是出色的同学 优秀的导师
I was doing well academically.
我成绩优异
I was doing well in athletics.
擅长体育运动
i was playing varsity squash at the time.
我当时在校队打壁球
I was doing well socially.
社交也游刃有余
Everything was going well.
一切都很顺利
Except for the fact.
除了一点
That I was unhappy.
我不快乐
And I didn't understand why.
而且我不明白为什么
It was then in a matter of moments,
也就是在那时
that I decided that I had to find out why and become happier.
我决定要找出原因 变得快乐
And that was when I switched my concentration
于是我将研究方向
from computer science to philosophy and psychology
从计算机科学转向了哲学及心理系
with a single question:
目标只有一个
how can I become happier?
如何变得更快乐?
Over time I did become happier.
渐渐地 我的确变得更快乐了
What contributed most to my happiness was when I encountered a new emerging field
主要因为我接触了一个新的领域
that at that time didn't have the name that it has today.
那时并未正式命名
But essentially research that falls under or within the field of positive psychology.
但本质上属于积极心理学范畴
Positive psychology, studying it,
研究积极心理学
applying the ideas to my life has made me significantly happier.
把其理念应用到生活中 让我无比快乐
It continues to make me happier.
而且这种快乐继续着
And it was when I realized the impact that it had on me that I decided to share it with others.
于是我决定将其与更多的人分享
That's when I decided that I wanted to be a teacher and teach in this field.
选择教授这门学科
So this is positive psychology,
这就是积极心理学
psychology 1504.
1504号心理学课程
And we'll be exploring this new,
我们将一起探索这一全新
relatively new and fascinating field.
相对新兴 令人倾倒的领域
And hopefully, we will be exploring more than the field ourselves.
希望同时还能探索我们自己
When I first taught this class that was back in 2002,
我第一次开设这门课程 是在2002年
I taught it at a seminar and had eight students.
是以讨论会的形式 只有8名学生
Two dropped out.
两名退出了
That left me with six.
只剩我和其他六个人
The year after,
一年后
the class became slightly larger.
学生稍微多了一点
I had over three hundred students.
有300多人参加
And then third year when I taught it which was the last time,
到了第三年 也就是上一次开课
I had 850 students in the class,
有850人参加
making it at that point the largest course at Harvard.
是当时哈佛人数最多的课程
And that's when the media became interested.
这引起了媒体的关注
Because they wanted to understand why.
因为他们想知道为什么
They wanted to understand this phenomenon that "here you have a class,
他们对这一奇特现象非常好奇
that's larger than Introduction to Economics".
"竟然有比经济学导论更热门的课程
How could that be?
怎么可能呢?"
So I was invited by the media for interviews,
于是我被请去参加各类媒体采访
whether it was newspapers, radio, television.
报纸 广播 电视
And I started to notice a pattern during those interviews.
从这些采访中 我发现了一种有趣的模式
So I would walk into the interview.
我前去参加采访
We would have the interview.
进行采访
And afterwards, the producer or the interviewer would walk me out
结束后 制片人或主持人会送我出来
and say something to the effects of "well thank you Tal for the interview.
说些诸如"Tal 多谢你抽空参加采访
But you know I expected you to be different".
"不过你跟我想象的不太一样"的话
And I would ask, as nonchalant as I could of course.
我漫不经心地问
I didn't really care but had to ask anyway,
我无所谓 不过总得回应
"how different?" And they would say,
"有何不同?" 他们会说
"Well you know, we expected you to be more outgoing."
"这个嘛 我们以为你很外向"
Next interview, the end of the interview, same thing.
下一次采访 结束时仍是如此
"Thank you for doing the interview.
"多谢接受采访
But you know Tal, I expected you to be different."
"不过Tal 你跟我想象得不太一样"
And once again, nonchalant of course.
又一次 我漫不经心地问
would ask"how different?"
"有何不同?"
And she would say,
她说
"Well you know, we expected you to be less, less itrovert."
"这个嘛 我们没想到你会这么内向"
Next interview, same thing.
下一次采访 仍是如此
"How different?"
"有何不同?"
"Well, you know, more extroverted. More outgoing."
"这个嘛 更开朗 更外向"
Next interview. "Well, you know, less shy."
下一次采访 "这个嘛 太害羞了"
Coz I get very nervous in interviews.
因为采访中我容易紧张
Interview after interview, literally dozens.
差不多有几十次采访
More outgoing, more cheerful.
每次都是"好交际 更开朗"
Less introverted, more extroverted.
"不含蓄 更外向"
And on and on.
诸如此类
But here is the best one.
最绝的一次
So this is one of the local channels here around Boston.
是波士顿一家地方台
I was going to the interview.
我去参加采访
We had a quite long interview,
聊了很多
which I thought was actually pretty good.
我觉得进行得不错
And at the end of the interview,
采访结束
the interviewer is a very jolly guy.
主持人是个热情开朗的男生
He walks me out and puts his hands on my shoulder,
他送我出门 拍着我的肩说
and says, "thank you very much for doing the interview."
"多谢接受我们采访"
And then the usual comes.
然后又是那句
"But you know Tal, I expected you to be different."
"不过 Tal 你跟我想象得不太一样"
And I said,
我问
"How different?" Just so you understand,
"有何不同" 你要知道
by this time, my self-esteem is short.
那时候 我已经完全被打击了
But still with some resemblance of nonchalance I asked,
不过我还是漫不经心地问
"how different?"
"有何不同?"
And he looks at me and says,
他看着我说
"Well I don't know Tal. I expected you to be taller."
"我也说不上 Tal 我以为你会更高些"
Taller? What?
更高些?什么?
Five seven, well ok five six and a half is not enough to teach happiness?
1米70...是1米69不够格传授快乐吗
And I thought about it. I thought about it a lot.
我考虑了很久 仔细思量了
The whole pattern from the beginning.
整件事从头到尾
And I think I understand why they expected someone different.
我似乎明白为什么他们期望不同了
You see they had to explain to themselves as well as the audience,
因为他们要说服自己 说服观众
"how come this lecture is larger than the Introduction to Economics?"
"这门课怎么会比经济学导论更热门?"
And the way to explain it must be that
唯一的解释就是
the teacher is very outgoing,
导师非常外向
extremely charismatic,
充满领袖气质
very cheerful and extrovert and of course, tall.
乐观开朗 当然了 还很高
Well, there is one L missing there.
可惜我的名字少了一个L
But...
但是
Yeah.
是啊
If only.
真可惜
So the problem though is
所以问题是
that they were looking in the wrong place for the explanation.
他们找答案找错了地方
In other words, they were looking at the messenger.
也就是说 他们不该关注信息传达者
What they needed to look at was the message.
而应该关注信息本身
Now how do I know that?
我怎么知道的呢
You see because I see other positive psychology classes on other campuses
因为我参与过其他大学积极心理学课
around the country and around the world.
遍及全国 乃至全球
There are over 200 hundred campuses here in United States that teach positive psychology.
美国有超过200所大学开设了本课程
On almost every campus where this class is taught,
而且几乎其中所有院校 这门课
it's either one of the or the largest class.
都是参与人数最多的或者最多的之一
It's about the message.
信息是关键
I see more and more organizations taking up positive psychology in their,
越来越多的机构组织开设这门课
as consultant companies,
还有咨询公司
some of them the leading big consultant companies are taking it on.
其中一些甚至是全球知名咨询公司
More and more high schools are introducing positive psychology class.
越来越多的中学开始引入积极心理学
Elementary schools are introducing it.
小学也是
The governments around the world are expressing interest in this new emerging field.
各国政府都对这一新领域表现出兴趣
Why? Because it works.
为什么?因为它有效
Because it really works.
它的的确确有效
You see this whole realm on life flourishing,
殷盛人生 快乐 幸福感这一整个领域
on happiness, on well-being has been until recently dominated by the self-health movement.
在此之前一直被心理自助运动统治
What do we have in the self-health movement?
心理自助运动带来了什么
We have books that are very interesting,
生动有趣
that are very accessible.
通俗易懂的书籍
We have speakers who are very outgoing,
热情外向的宣讲者
very charismatic and tall,
颇具领袖气质 且身材高大
attracting the masses into these workshops, seminars and lectures.
吸引大众参与他们的专题讨论讲座
But, there is a very big "but" here.
但是 有一个大大的转折
Many of these books, many of these workshops and seminars lack substance.
其中许多书籍讨论都缺少实质内容
Very often, overpromising and under-delivering.
通常都言过其实 无法兑现
So these are five things you need to know to be happy.
比如 快乐的五个关键
The three things to be the great leader.
成功领袖的三个要素
The one secret of success, happiness and a perfect love life.
成功 快乐 完美爱情的唯一秘诀
Overpromising. Under-delivering.
夸大其词 效果甚微
On the other hand, we have academia.
再来说说学术界
What do we have in academia?
学术界给我们带来了什么
We have a lot of rigor, a lot of substance.
大量精确的实质内容
We have datas analyzed, reanalyzed and meta-analyzed.
数据被一而再 再而三地反复分析
Things that actually work, good stuff.
行之有效的好东西
But, and there is also a very big "but" here.
但是 又有一个大大的转折
Very few people read refereed academic journals.
很少有人会阅读专业学术期刊
I mean Think about it: how many people outside this room of course
想想看 这间教室之外有多少人
have read the last twelve issues of the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology?
读过最近12期《个性与社会心理学》杂志?
Most people don't even know what that means.
大多数人甚至不知道那是什么东西
The head of my PHD programs actually estimated the average academic journal article
我博士班的主任估算过
is read by seven people.
学术期刊上的一篇论文平均只有7人阅读
You know...
这话...
And that includes the author's mother.
其中还包括作者的母亲
So you know I say half in jest but it's actually really sad.
这话虽然是半开玩笑 但其实很可悲
Because...certainly sad for me, as an academic.
因为...作为学者 我觉得很可悲
Because these things are good.
因为这些论文都非常精彩
They are important.
非常重要
These things make a difference,
能大有作为
can even make more of a difference.
甚至不仅仅是作为
But not accessible to most people.
但是对大众来说晦涩难懂
And this is where positive psychology comes in.
所以我们需要积极心理学
And this is also where this class comes in.
需要这门课程
The explicit mandate of positive psychology as well as of this class
积极心理学及本课程的宗旨非常明确
is to create a bridge between Ivory tower and mainstreet.
就是要在象牙塔及大众间构建桥梁
In other words, it is to bring the rigor,
换句话说 就是要把严谨
the substance, the empirical foundation,
实质 经验基础
the science from academia
学术科学
and merge it with accessibility of the self-help or New Age movement.
与自助或新纪元运动的通俗易懂相结合
In a way the best of both worlds.
充分发挥两者所长
And this explains the popularity of the field of positive psychology:
这也是积极心理学大受欢迎的原因:
science that works.
有用的科学
This class will be taught on two levels.
本课程将分为两个部分
The first level it will be taught as any other class in psychology
第一部分会和其他心理学
or any of the classes you've taken here.
或者其他任何课程一样
You'll be introduced here to studies,
我将向你们介绍相关知识
to research, to rigorous academic work.
调查研究 严谨的学术作品
You'll be writing paper, academic paper.
需要你们撰写报告 学术论文
You'll be taking exams.
参加考试
Just like every other class.
跟其他课程一样
But then it will also be taught at the second level,
而教学内容的另一部分
which is for every paper that you'll read,
你们读每一篇论文
every paper that you'll write,
写每一篇论文时
you'll always be thinking,
都需要思考
"Ok, how can I take these ideas and apply them to my life?
如何把这些理念运用到生活中去
How can I apply them to my relationship?
运用到恋爱中去
How can I apply them to my community?"
运用到社交圈里去
Two levels.
就是这两个部分
The academic. Applied.
学术与应用
I did not just introduce whether it's in the readings or in the lectures ideas
无论是论文还是讲座 我不会因为
just because they are interesting for the sake of the idea.
某个理论有趣而去介绍它
It is always an idea that is both rigorous and can be applied.
而是因为这个理论严谨且能被应用
Just a few words about housekeeping.
再唠叨几句题外话
Some of the questions that I have already received from you before the class started.
有几个问题课前就有人问我了
So this, unfortunately,
不幸的是这学期将是我最后一次
is the last time that I am teaching positive psychology or any other class for that matter at Harvard.
在哈佛开设积极心理学或其他课程
Hopefully within two years, probably not next year,
但愿两年内 明年可能性不大
but within two years,
但是两年内
there will be positive psychology class offered,
学校会再次开设积极心理学课程
but I certainly cannot guarantee it.
但我无法保证
About feedback and questions.
关于反馈与提问
If you have any questions, anything that's not clear,
如果你有任何问题或不明白的地方
if you agree or disagree with something,
如果你同意或反对什么观点
email me or email your TF (Teaching Fellow at Harvard, just like TA at other schools)
请给我或助教写邮件
and we'll always respond.
我们一定会回复的
Sometimes if the question is asked by enough people,
如果某个问题问的人数较多
we'll respond to it publicly.
我们会公开回答
Always anonymously.
当然一定是匿名的
Unless you specified specifically that your name can be mentioned.
除非你特别注明可以提及你的名字
Sometimes you may be listening to a lecture and then half way through it there is an emergency.
有时候讲座过程中 突然有紧急情况
There is something that you really have to ask,
有什么非问不可的问题
something that cannot wait.
无法等待
In that case, please just put your hand up.
如果那样的话 请直接举手
Coz it's just like when you have to go to the bathroom.
因为就跟你要去厕所一样
Just can't stop.
无法忍耐
Can't wait.
无法等待
And when you gotta go,
要去
you gotta go.
就去
So we'll take a positive psychology break for that.
我们会为此进行积极心理休息
And just stop me half way through and I'll answer any question.
所以大可以打断我 我会回答任何问题
All the power points, as well as the videos of the classes will be online.
所有幻灯片以及课程视频都会放在网上
Will be available within couple of days.
课后几天就能下载
Well the power points will be available before,
幻灯片其实课前就能下载
say for this lecture it will be before so that you can use them in class.
这样你上课时就能用到
The videos, unfortunately, cannot be made available before. We tried.
可惜视频不能提前提供 我们试了
Couldn't figure it out.
但效果不好
So it will be available within a day or two after.
所以会在课后一两天内放到网上
And the reason why they are up there.
这样做的原因
First of all, I do prefer that you attend lecture.
首先 我当然更希望你们出席课程
I do prefer that you are physically here.
能出现在课堂里
You get things in the energy of the room with so many students
和大家一起 在课堂的气氛中学习
so you wouldn't just get from your computer.
而不是仅仅对着电脑
The reason why I do put them up is so that you have the opportunity
我之所以把资料放在网上是为了
if you want to see it again or if you have to miss a class.
让你们可以重温或者学习错过的课程
That's perfectly fine.
这很正常
And also because,
另一个原因
and this is also the reason why the power points are always available,
之所以提前提供幻灯片
I want you to be engaged in the material.
我希望你们能充分理解材料
I want you to be engaged in whatever it is that we are discussing in class.
充分参与课堂讨论
Not necessarily thinking about getting down every word that I say on paper,
而不是忙于记录我说的每一个字
remembering everything, memorizing everything.
记住每一个词 背诵每一句话
I want you to take rather than passive notes of writing down
我不希望你们被动地记录
what is on the power point or every word that I say.
幻灯片上的内容或者我说的话
I'd like you to take active notes.
而是要主动记录
And that means being engaged with the material.
也就是要充分理解材料
For example, if you heard something and idea and you say,
比如 如果你们听到某个理论 觉得
"Oh, that's interesting."
"挺有趣的"
Star it. Write it down.
标上星号 写下来
Or "Ok I think I'll start applying this."
或者觉得"也许我可以应用这点"
Write it down.
那就写下来
"Or I want to tell my mom about this later."
或者"跟我妈妈讲讲"
Or "I want to talk to my roommates or my team about this idea."
或者"跟我室友队友讲讲"
Write it down.
那就写下来
Active note-taking is opposed to passive note-taking for two reasons.
主动笔记与被动笔记有两方面不同
First of all, as I said,
首先 正如我刚才说的
this class is a class about making a difference in people's lives.
这门课是关于如何改变生活
I would not be teaching the class just for its academic beauty,
我不会仅为了学术之美而教授此课
although there is a lot of academic beauty in this field.
虽然这一领域的确有许多学术之美
So write down if you have an idea that you think you can apply.
所以发现可以实际运用的 就写下来
The second reason why we should that is because you'll remember more.
第二个原因是 你会记住更多
Better attention, better understanding of the material if you are actively engaged,
主动参与 集中注意 更好地理解材料
as opposed to just taking down passive notes.
而不是被动做笔记
Throughout the class,
在这整个课程中
starting next week,
从下周开始
we'll take what I called,
我们将进行我所说的
"time-ins" as opposed to "time-outs".
"练习时间" 而不是"休息时间"
it's like a time-out.
其实类似"休息时间"
It's the time where we stop the class and you look inward.
这段时间会我们停止课程 进行内省
And this is literally a time of silence in a class.
也就是课堂上的安静时刻
I will stop for a minute or two.
我会停一两分钟
And you'll have a chance either to just stare at me or anyone else,
你们可以盯着我或者周围人发呆
or think about what we've just discussed,
或者思考一下之前讨论的内容
or have a guiding question that I will provide you that you'll address during the class.
或者解答我提出的提示问题
The reason why I have "Time-ins"...
之所以进行"练习时间"
This is something that I am introducing this year for the first time.
这是今年新提出的
We didn't have it last time.
上学期并没有
It's because over the last two years since I last taught it,
因为上次课程结束后到现在的两年
I've done a lot work in the area of silence.
我做了大量关于安静的研究
I've read a lot of research in this area about the importance of quiet times whether it's in a class,
关于安静时刻的重要性 无论是课堂里
in a lecture, whether it is at home,
讲座里 还是家中
whether it is for a leader in the business,
无论是对公司领导
for relationship, for children starting from pre-schools.
爱情关系 甚至学龄前儿童
Now many of you,
你们中很多人
as you are going through these "time-ins" if you decide to take this class may think,
在经历"练习时间"时可能会疑惑
"Well, is this what I'm paying 40,000 dollars a year for?
"我一年付四万美金就是为了这个?"
To sit a class and be quiet?"
"坐在教室里发呆?"
First of all, it will only be a minute or two at a time,
首先 每次只有一两分钟
maybe once or twice a lecture.
一堂课最多不超过两次
But second,
第二 这可能是
it is maybe the most important thing you'll take from this class.
你从本课程中学到的最重要的东西
The notion of embracing stillness.
即享受安静这一理念
Let me read to you an excerpt from a study that was run by two MIT professors.
我来读一段麻省理工两位教授的研究
By the way, all the names that I read and that are not on the power points,
我所提到名字不会出现在幻灯片上
you don't need to remember or write down.
不必背诵或记录
This is just for your edification.
只是为了启发你们
So David Foster and Matthew Wilson.
David Foster和Matthew Wilson教授
Both of them are from MIT.
都来自麻省理工大学
Indeed the following study that I think confirms the importance of "time-in",
他们研究证实了"练习时间"的重要性
time to look inside.
开始内省的时间
What they did is they scanned the brains of rats
他们在老鼠处在迷宫中及脱离迷宫后
while they were in a maze and after they went through the maze.
分别对它们进行了脑扫描
And here's what they found.
以下是他们的发现
"What the results suggest is that while there certainly is some record of your experience
实验结果表明 当某种经历正在进行时
as it is occurring. in other words when they were doing the maze,
即老鼠进行迷宫时
the actual learning C
真正的学习阶段
when you try to figure out:
是当你尝试分辨
'What was important? What should I keep and throw away?'
什么才是重要的 什么舍弃什么保留
C that happens after the fact,
这些发生在经历之后
during periods of quiet wakeful introspection.
进行安静的自省时
What they show was rats who went through the maze
他们的实验表明
and went through the maze again and again,
接连不断反复进入迷宫的老鼠
learned far less than rats who took time aside,
比进行一次迷宫后
chilled out a little bit after a maze,
稍事放松 来点小酒的老鼠
had more margarita.
学到的少得多
Experience, embrace stillness.
经历 享受安静
This has implications and they showed implications to human beings as well.
这很能说明问题 对人类也一样
Not only those of the rat race,
不仅仅是实验小白鼠
all human beings.
所有人类都是
So what they say is that "replay might constitute a general mechanism of learning and memory".
他们认为"重现可能形成一种学习记忆机制"
Both learning, understanding,
包括学习 理解
as well as memory, retention.
记忆 保留
When we reflect, when we replay the material,
当我们思考时 我们重放素材时
we are much more likely to retain,
更容易保留
to remember what we have just been through.
记住之前的经历
So the importance of time aside cannot be over-emphasized.
所以休息时间的重要性不能被忽视
In his wonderful book of teaching,
Parker Palmer在他的教学著作
Parker Palmer-- it's called The Courage to Teach,
《教学的勇气》一书中
says the following--
提到了以下一段话
Words are not the sole medium of exchange in teaching and learning.
语言不是教学的唯一媒介
We educate with silence as well.
安静同样可以进行教育
Silence gives us a chance to reflect on what we have said and heard.
安静让我们有机会反省我们所说所闻
In authentic education,
在真正的教育中
silence is treated as a trustworthy matrix for the inner work students must do,
安静为学生进行内省提供可靠环境
a medium for learning of the deepest sort."
是一种最深层次的学习媒介
Silence is something that is missing from our culture.
而安静恰恰是我们文化所缺失的
I know that many of you have probably read Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance,
很多人可能读过《万里任禅游》
Robert M. Pirsig.
作者Robert M Pirsig
He had a second book out,
还写过另一本书
less well-known, called Lila (Lila: an Inquiry into Morals).
没那么知名 叫《寻找莱拉》
And Lila is an anthropological study of Native Americans.
这本书是对印第安人的人类学研究
What he does there is compare their culture to Americans' from European ancestry.
将他们的文化与美国传承的欧洲文化进行对比
And one of the distinguishing characteristics between these two cultures
两种文化最突出的特点之一是
is their approach were silence.
印第安人崇尚安静
What he found was when he went and sat around with Native Americans.
他发现和印第安人坐在一起
They would sit around the fire and hang out for two,
他们围坐在篝火边两三个小时
three hours without saying a word.
一句话也没说
Just sit around.
只是坐在那儿
Look at one another.
看着对方
Smile. Have a good time.
微笑 享受美好时光
Introspect.
内省
Just be there for hours.
就这样几个小时
While he points out that in our culture we feel very uncomfortable with the absence of words,
他指出 在我们文化中沉默
with the absence of sound or noise.
让人不适
We have to fill up all the gaps.
我们试图打破沉默
This is an important cultural difference.
这是一项重要的文化差异
And we pay a price for this lack of stillness.
我们为缺乏安静付出了代价
A price that we'll talk about a lot,
我们会重点讨论这一代价
when I talk about relationships,
涉及到恋爱
when I talk about virtue and morality
美德与道德
and when we talk about happiness and wellbeing in general.
以及快乐与幸福感
Let me give a little bit background on positive psychology:
下面介绍一下积极心理学的背景
how we came about and how this class came about.
它是如何诞生的 这门课是如何诞生的
In many ways, positive psychology is the brainchild,
从很多方面来说 积极心理学是
the product and the grandchild of humanistic psychology.
人本主义心理学的产物和衍生
What we have in humanistic psychology is essentially a reaction
人本主义心理学本质上是
to the existing psychologies of the time.
对当时各种心理学派系的不同意见
The founders, considered the founders of humanistic psychology
人本主义心理学的创始人
in fact called it "the third force".
称之为心理学上的"第三势力"
Why the "third force"?
为什么是"第三势力"
Because the first force was behaviorism.
因为第一势力是行为主义
The work of Skinner (B. F. Skinner),
代表人物有斯金纳
the work of Watson (John B. Watson),
华生
the work of Thorndik (Edward Thorndik).
桑代克
This was the first force.
这是第一势力
The second force was psychoanalysis.
第二势力是精神分析学
The work of Freud (Sigmund Freud), Jung (Carl Jung), Adler (Alfred Adler) to some extent.
创建者包括弗洛伊德 荣格以及阿德勒
This was the second force.
这是第二势力
And the third force,
第三势力
humanistic psychology came as a reaction to it.
人本主义心理学作为对其的异议出现
First it is a reaction to behaviorism.
首先是对行为主义的异议
Behaviorism looks at the human entity,
行为主义认为人的主体性
at the person as basically a collection of behaviors as a box,
认为人是一个行为集合
like a billiard ball knocked around by reinforcements,
就像一只被击打而四处滚动的台球
by punishment, by reward.
被增强 奖惩驱动
And what humanistic psychology said was that
而人本主义心理学认为
we are much more than a billiard ball being knocked around.
我们不只是被击打的台球
We have spirit. We have a soul.
我们有精神 有灵魂
We have cognitions and thoughts that matter.
我们有重要的认知与思想
It's not just behavior that is important for understanding as well as improving life.
不能只靠行为观察 改善人生
And then psychoanalysis, the second force.
然后是第二势力精神分析学
The psychoanalysis is about basically understanding mostly through the subconscious:
精神分析学主要通过潜意识分析
that's how you understand it;
它决定你的理解
that's how you improve the quality of life.
决定如何改善生活
There are defense mechanisms,
还有防卫机制
there are biological instincts, neurosis--
人类本能论 神经症
and if you understand these very often dark forces,
如果你理解这些黑暗势力
were better able to deal with life:
就能更好地处理生活
understand as well as improve the quality of life.
了解并改善生活质量
Humanistic psychology says human beings are much more than that.
人本主义心理学认为人类不止如此
Much more than biological instincts,
不仅仅是生理本能
much more than neurosis,
不仅仅是神经症
much more than the person who exists in a Newtonian reality like a billiard ball.
不仅仅是牛顿学说世界里的台球
We need to value much more the human being.
我们要重视人的本质
We need to give much more dignity and freedom to the person.
给予人更多的自尊和自由
There was a problem.
但有一个问题
The problem was humanistic psychology is said lacked the rigorous methodology.
人本主义心理学缺少严谨的方法论
While it brought in many wonderful ideas,
但它引入了许多精彩的理念
talked about the study of well-being,
对于幸福感的研究
talked about the study of optimism,
乐观主义的研究
of kindness, of morality, of virtue,
善良 道德 美德
of love, of relationships, of peak experiences,
爱 两性关系 巅峰体验
of self-actualization, of empathy.
自我实现 移情
All these wonderful concepts that we'll talk about throughout the semester.
这些精彩的概念都会在本学期探讨
It wasn't as rigorous about its epistemology,
它的认识论并不严谨
about how we form ideas and how we learn.
如何形成理念 如何学习
And that's why, in many ways, largely,
所以在很多方面 大部分
not completely but largely more of into the self-health movement.
不完全但大部分成为了自助运动
Interesting ideas, good ideas, important ideas,
有趣 有益 重要的理念
certainly good intentions,
意图当然是好的
but to some extent,
但就某种程度上
without the academic rigor.
缺乏学术严谨性
And that's why it lacked the impact on academia.
所以它在学术上影响很小
That's why we don't have partly any humanistic psychology classes offered in universities today.
所以很少有大学开设人本主义心理学
There are very few still around.
几乎没有
And this is why also a lot of it became the New Age essentially.
所以本质上成为了新纪元运动
But still,
但是
it's humanistic psychology that has in many ways fathered and mothered,
我们很快会了解到 人本主义心理学
as we'll see, positive psychology.
孕育了积极心理学
So let's meet the grandparents.
然我们先见见祖父祖母
People like Rollo May. People like Carl Rogers.
比如Rollo May和Carl Rogers
And more than anyone, Abraham Maslow.
还有最著名的Abraham Maslow
Was the American Psychological Association President.
曾是美国心理学会主席
Was the professor just down the road here at Brandeis (Brandeis University).
布兰迪斯大学教授
And he introduced this humanistic psychology in 1954.
他于1954年提出了人本主义心理学
He wrote a chapter, called "Toward the Positive Psychology".
他写了一章《为了积极心理学》
1954. In it he said we need to also research kindness,
1954年 他在其中写到 我们需要研究
goodness and happiness and optimism.
善良 美德 快乐与乐观
In many ways it was way ahead of his time.
可以说这是超前于他时代的
Then if Maslow is the grandfather,
如果说Maslow是祖父
then Karen Horney is the grandmother.
那Karen Horney就是祖母了
Initially a psychoanalyst,
她最初是精神分析学者
trained through the works of Freud,
学习弗洛伊德的理论
she realized the focuses had been too much on the negative--
意识到其过于注重消极面
on neurosis, on psychosis and said we also,
神经症 精神病 她认为
not only but also have to focus on what is working on human organism.
还必须关注影响人类生命体的东西
We have to work and look at the fine qualities and cultivate those.
我们需要研究培养那些好的品质
Because part of being human is being those things as well.
因为它们也是我们的一部分
In many ways, brought about the movement toward humanistic psychology and through that--
反而向人本主义靠近了 并由此产生了
positive psychology.
积极心理学
Aaron Antonovsky,
还有Aaron Antonovsky
the third person I would consider the grandfather,
第三位祖父级人物
brought in the idea of focusing on health.
提出了关注健康的理念
He has a new concept.
他提出了一个新概念
Or he introduced a new concept.
或者说他引进了一个新概念
I'm still here. Don't worry.
我还在 别担心
He introduced a new concept, which he called--
他引进了一个新概念 他称之为
his own neologism,
他个人创造的新词
"salutogenesis".
健康本源学
Salutogenesis: saluto--(which is) health; geneis (which is) origin.
由两部分组成 saluto健康 geneis起源
The origin of health.
健康的起源
And this was an alternative model,
这是病理学常规模型的
to the conventional ways model of pathologies.
替代模型
So instead of just studying pathologies
也就是说除了研究病理学
whether it's in physical health or psychological health,
无论是生理健康 还是心理健康
we should also study the origin of health.
还需要研究健康的起源
In many ways that is what prevented medicine is about.
这也是预防医学所关注的
So this was a novel idea back in 1970s when he introduced it.
这在1970年代 是一个全新的理念
And we'll talk a lot about Aaron Antonovsky.
我们会仔细讨论Aaron Antonovsky
Now the parents.
现在转到父辈
Martin Seligman, considered the father of the positive psychology,
Martin Seligman被认为是积极心理学之父
network of scholars,
与一群相关学者
started the field in 1998.
于1998年确立了这一领域
Like Maslow, he too, was the President of American Psychological Association.
和马斯洛一样 也是美国心理协会会长
And as his mandate, during his presidency,
他任职期间的首要任务
he had two aims:
是实现两个目标
the first aim-- to make academic psychology more accessible,
第一 让学院式心理学变得通俗
-- in other words--
也就是说
bridge Ivory tower and mainstream.
连接起象牙塔与普罗大众
This was the first aim of his presidency.
这是他任职期间的第一目标
The second aim was introduce a positive psychology.
第二 是引进一个积极的心理学
A psychology that will look at also things that work,
需要着眼于有用的东西
that were not just study--
不仅仅是研究
depression, anxiety, schizophrenia and neurosis.
抑郁 焦虑 精神分裂 神经症
A psychology a network of scholars who will focus on
还需要关注
-- love, relationships, self-esteem,
爱 两性关系 自尊
motivation, resilience and well-being.
动机 恢复以及幸福感
And he introduced these ideas
他提出了这些理念
and it's all been literally uphill from then.
从那时起便蓬勃发展起来
Before Martin Seligman,
在Martin Seligman之前
this all happened in 1998 and we'll talk about it a little bit more next time.
都发生在1998年 下次我们会详谈
This all  happened in 1998.
这都诞生于1998年
Long before 1998,
而早在1998年前
our very own professor Ellen Langer did research in all these areas,
Ellen Langer教授就已研究了这些领域
bringing the humanistic spirit and combining it with the academic scientific rigor.
将人本主义精神与学术科学严谨性结合
We'll be talking probably more than any other scholar about her work in this class.
我们对她的讨论会比对其他人多
And another person from Harvard,
还有一位哈佛的教授
one of the parents of positive psychology was Philip Stone,
积极心理学的另一位父辈 Philip Stone
who passed away two years ago, yesterday.
两年前的昨天去世了
Both Langer and Stone were my physicist advisors,
两位都是我的物理学导师
introduced me to the field of positive psychology into this research.
带我进入了积极心理学领域的研究
In 1998 when I had the first positive psychology summit,
1998年我第一次参加积极心理学峰会
Professor Stone took me along with him.
Stone教授带我同去
I was a graduate student.
我那时在攻读硕士学位
In 1999 he taught the first positive psychology class at Harvard,
1999年 他首次在哈佛开设了本课程
one of the first in the world.
在全球范围内也是首批
I was his teaching fellow.
我是他的教研员
A couple of years later, he taught it again.
两年后 他又重新开设了课程
Again I was his teaching fellow.
我仍旧担任教研员
And then when I graduated,
后来我毕业了
he suggested I take over his class.
他提议我接手他的课程
And here we are today.
直到今天
So this is 1504.
这就是1504号心理学课程
Let me give you a sense of,
我再来讲讲...
in the next half an hour and so,
接下来的半小时
a sense of what you expect in this class.
我会向你们介绍下这门课的内容
The first thing is this class is not just about information,
首先 这门课不光是传授信息
it is also explicitly about transformation.
而且关于如何变形 显而易见
What do I mean by that?
这是什么意思
You see most of education today is about information.
如今大多数教育都只是传达信息
What is information?
什么是信息
So we have a container,
比如 我们有一个容器
which is our mind.
也就是我们的思想
And information is about taking data,
信息就是接收数据
taking science, taking information and putting it inside the form.
接收科学 接收信息 储存到容器里
That is information.
这就是信息
Now when this form is filled,
等容器填满了
that's when we are educated.
我们就毕业了
More information, more data, better.
信息数据越多越好
Not enough.
这还不够
Because it's not just information that determines our wellbeing,
因为信息无法决定我们的幸福感
our success, our self-esteem, our motivational level,
我们的成功 自尊 动机水平
the relationship and the quality of our relationships.
两性关系及其质量
It's much more than information.
光有信息还不够
Transformation is about taking this form and changing it.
变形则是把容器的形状改变
Trans, (which is) change, form, (which is) shape.
"trans"即改变 "form"即形状
Change the form.
改变形状
This is transformation.
这就是变形
This is the distinction that I learned first from at the school Professor Robert Kegan
这是Robert Kegan教授
who taught about this.
教我的第一区别
Information in and of itself is not enough.
接收信息 关注信息本身是不够的
Think about this example.
听听这个例子
You go for an athletic meet.
你去参加运动会
Your aim is to get into the top three--
目标是进入前三
to be a medalist.
获得奖牌
You come in number eight.
但是只获得第八名
What's the analysis?
你会如何分析
What's the interpretation? -- Terrible.
你会如何解读? 太糟糕了
I just failed.
我彻底失败了
You feel deflated. Enervated.
你灰心丧气 感到无力
On the other hand,
但从另一角度看
the exact same event.
同样的比赛
You came eight when you expected to be top three.
你期望获得前三 但只得到第八
You can interpret it as "Ok, so what have I learned?
你可以解读为"我学到了什么?
I need to work even harder."
我还需要更努力地训练"
You become more energized.
你会更有动力
You learned from the experience.
从经验中学习
In other words, the same objective information which is
也就是说 同样的客观信息
"I got eighth; I expected top three".
"我是第八名 我目标前三"
The same information,
同样的信息
very different interpretation.
截然不同的解读
One is a disaster,
一个认为是灾难
the other interpretation is an opportunity.
另一个则当成机遇
One leads to loss of energy,
一个让人失去动力
the other one to increasing energy.
另一个增加动力
Or think about another very common example.
还有一个很普遍的例子
We know of many people around the world who seemingly have everything,
世界各地很多人似乎拥有了一切
who are doing well,
人生顺利
who have more than they need.
生活富庶
And yet they are unhappy.
但仍旧不快乐
And then there are people around the world who have very little.
而另一些人拥有的不多
And yet they never cease,
但从未中断
never stop to celebrate life.
从未停止享受人生
And we have another way around as well.
还有相反的情况
People who have everything and appreciate it and enjoy life.
拥有一切的人 充满感恩 享受生活
People who have very little and who see themselves as victim.
生活窘迫的人觉得自己是受害者
In other words, it's not just the information that goes in.
也就是说 重要的不仅仅是获得了什么信息
It's also the shape,
还有是何形状
the interpretation, the perception, the focus.
如何解读 如何理解 关注的重点
And that is determined by the shape of the form.
这就是由容器的形状所决定的
This is what I realized when I was an undergrad here.
这是我在本科生阶段所认识到的
Seemingly, looking in from the outside, I had everything.
表面上看 我拥有了一切
Doing well (in) sports,
体育运动
academics and socially.
学术 社交都很成功
And yet my perception,
但是我对生命的理解
my focus, my interpretation of life-- not that great.
关注和解读并不正面
I wasn't happy.
我不快乐
The interpretation matters very often a lot more as we'll see than the information that goes in.
我们后面会讲 通常解读比信息更重要
One of the sentences that I'll repeat throughout the class is that
有一句话我会在课程中经常引用
happiness is much more contingent on our state of mind than our status or the state of our bank account.
快乐由我们的精神状态而定 而不是社会地位或银行存款
And that's where transformation comes in.
所以需要变形
And that's why it's so important for wellbeing.
这对建立幸福感来说很重要
What that will look like in practice
所以我们在实际操作时
is that we'll cover not so much information.
不会传达过多信息方面的东西
We'll uncover much more and I don't mean that in the Berkeley (George Berkeley) sense of the word.
而是挖掘更多东西 不是联想意义上的
I mean that in the academic sense of the word.
而是学术意义上的
In other words,
也就是说
what we'll do is uncover potential that we have inside,
我们要挖掘自身潜能
that we have inside of us all along.
这种潜能一直存在
Maybe we just didn't see.
只是我们没有发现
Or maybe it's obscured by something or another.
或者被其他东西掩盖了
We'll uncover it so that we can utilize it,
我们要发现利用它
so that we can focus on it,
以便关注它
so that we can perceive it.
以便理解它
Here is a story just to illustrate it.
我讲个故事来说明吧
So this is Michelangelo.
比如米开朗基罗
One day he was asked by a journalist of his time,
曾经有个记者问他
"how did you create this most amazing masterpiece, David?",
您是如何创造出《大卫》这件巨作的?
to which Michelangelo responded,
米开朗基罗回答
"it was easy.
很简单
I went to the quarry.
我去了趟采石场
I saw this huge piece of marble.
看见一块巨大的大理石
And in it I saw David.
我在它身上看到了大卫
All I needed to do was to chip away the excess stone,
我只要凿去多余的石头
to get rid of the marble that shouldn't have been there.
只留下有用的
And when I got rid of this excess stone, there was David.
凿去多余的石头之后 大卫就诞生了
" Not obviously easier said than done.
虽然说的比做的容易
But the story captured the metaphor of what this class very much is about.
但是这个故事抓住了这门课程精髓
It's about chipping away the excess stone.
即凿除多余石块
It's about getting rid of limitations, of barriers,
也就是摆脱限制 阻碍
whether it's the fear of failure,
或者对失败的恐惧
something that we didn't have as kids.
这些东西在并不是与生俱来的
But today most people in our culture have it.
但如今却出现在了大多数人身上
It's about chipping away perfectionism that is debilitating and often hurts us.
要凿除削弱甚至伤害我们的完美主义
It's about chipping away our ability for success,
凿除胜利的能力
because maybe we are afraid of success.
因为我们可能害怕胜利
Maybe we feel guilty about some of the things that we have in our life,
可能对生命中一些东西感到内疚
and that in turn limits us.
这些都会反过来限制我们
Maybe it's about chipping away the limitations on our relationships
也许甚至还要凿除两性关系中的限制
in while we don't thrive within them.
尤其是带来消极面的时候
This is what this class is mostly about.
这些就是本课程的主要内容
As Thoreau says,
就像梭罗说的那样
"soul grows more by subtraction than by addition",
"做减法比做加法让灵魂成长得更快"
by getting rid of these limitations,
减法包括除去那些
limitations that are preventing us from fulfilling our potential.
阻碍我们发挥潜能的限制
Because our potential is in there in nature.
因为我们的潜能是天生的
We talk a lot about human nature.
我们关注人类本性
It's there whether it's through God,
是与生俱来的 无论是上帝赐予的
whether it's through evolution.
还是进化产生的
We have a lot of potential that over time with we fix (?) stone of voices with being part of our culture
但是渐渐地受到外部文化压力
that very often these limitations are put on top of us just like the excess stone.
像多余石料一样 把我们禁锢起来了
Lao Tzu, "In pursuit of knowledge every day something is acquired.
老子说过
In pursuit of wisdom,
"为学日益
every day something is dropped."
为道日损"
Knowledge is about information.
"学"即信息
Wisdom is about transformation.
"道"即变形
I was recently interviewed for a newsletter on coaching
我最近参加一次大型咨询业会议时
before a large conference on the topic.
接受了一家相关期刊的采访
And the interviewer asked me,
采访者问我
"So what tips, what tools can you give from positive psychology?"
"能给读者传授些积极心理学建议吗"
So I talked about some of "the greatest hits":
于是我谈到了一些热门话题
the importance of gratitude,
感恩的重要性
the importance of physical exercise.
体育锻炼的重要性
I talked about the importance of spending time on our relationships,
我谈到了花时间经营爱情的重要性
about taking time aside and simplifying and so on and so on.
谈到了休息 简化 等等
As I was going through my long list,
我正滔滔不绝时
she stopped me and she said,
她打断了我 说
"You know Tal, this is all good.
谢谢 Tal 这些都不错
The importance of stuff, I know.
那些事情的重要性 我明白
But our readers already know that.
但这些我们的读者都已经知道了
I am looking for the Wow factor.
我想要的是轰动的因素
Come on, surprise me.
能让我意外的东西
What can you tell our readers?"
能否告诉我们的读者?"
And I thought about this question for a minute
我想了一会这个问题
and I realized that there is no Wow.
然后意识到根本没有什么惊奇可言
And I told her that,
我跟她这么说了
"you know if there is a wow, the wow is that there is no wow."
"所谓的轰动之处就是没有轰动之处"
That's it.
就是这样
Because the over-not-transformation emperor,
因为没有经过转变
the emperor of quick fixes has no clothes.
快速见效的说法都是皇帝的新衣
It doesn't exist.
是不存在的
it's over-promising and under-delivering.
是过高的承诺和过低的兑现
A life, a fulfilling life,
生活 令人满意的生活
a rich life includes ups and downs,
丰富的生活包括了起起落落
includes pain and getting up again,
包括了痛苦和再次振作
includes failure and getting up again.
包括了失败和再次奋斗
It includes success and celebrating it.
它包括了成功和庆祝成功
Victories and losses, ups and downs,
胜利和失败 起起和落落
as we'll talk about next week.
我们下个星期会讲到
It's not about this one secret.
而不是关乎一个秘密
One Wow to the good life.
一个能让人过上幸福生活的令人惊奇的诀窍
And many of the things you will learn in this class,
而你们将在本课程中学到的许多东西
you've heard of before.
都是你们之前听说过的
Probably nothing new to you.
也许对你来说没有什么新鲜的内容
You already know it inside of you.
在你内心深处你已经知道了
And you are going to say, "Well, it is common sense."
你会说"这是常识"
And yes, a lot of it is common sense.
是的 很多都是常识
However, it is Voltaire once said,
但是 伏尔泰曾经说过
"Common sense is not that common."
"常识并非那么平常"
And this especially applies to application.
特别是应用于实际
So the aim of this class is to make common sense more common,
所以本课程的目标是让常识更平常
especially in the real world application.
特别是应用到实际中
At the end of the class,
在本课程结束时
here's what I am hoping for,
我所希望的是
at the end of the class,
在本课程结束之时
if you decide to take it.
如果你打算上这门课的话
At the end of the semester,
在本学期结束时
I don't think-- I am not expecting you to come and tell me,
我不想 我不期待你跑来告诉我
"Wow! Thank you for teaching me so many new things."
"谢谢你教给了这么多新东西"
That's not what I am expecting.
那不是我所期待的
I don't think that is what will happen.
我不认为那会发生
What I hope will happen is for you to come and say,
我所希望发生的是你过来跟我说
rather than "thank you for teaching me",
不是说"谢谢你教了我"
something you would say
之类的话
"thank you for reminding me of something that I've already known".
而是"谢谢提醒了我一些我熟知事情"
And this is what this class is about.
这就是本课程要做的
It's constant reminder, twice a week.
经常性的提醒 一周两次
Constant reminder of what you already know,
经常提醒你们记起你们已知的东西
of what is inside you.
你们内心深处的东西
The David that is inside you.
你们心中的大卫
And what this class will hopefully do is to help you chip away some of these limitations,
本课程希望做到的是帮助你们凿掉一些束缚
whether it's limitation,
不管是哪种束缚
cognitive limitations that prevent you from seeing what you already knew,
是阻碍你认识已熟知事物的认知束缚
emotional limitations that are preventing you from deriving the benefits of what you already know,
还是阻碍你从已熟知事物中获取益处的情绪束缚
or behavioral limitations.
抑或是行为束缚
The ABC: affect, behavior, and cognition
基本要素是影响 行为和认知
that we'll talk about during the change week.
正是我们在改变周将要讨论的
So I'm making common sense more common.
我要让常识更平常
Information in and of itself is simply not enough.
信息本身还不够
It's not enough and what we need in addition to our information highway is a transformation highway.
还不够 而我们除了信息高速公路外还需要转变高速公路
Transformation high way,
是在转变高速公路
or transformation back roads,
还是转变乡村小道上
to come through the fast increasing pace.
来经历快速增长的步伐
Because as we'll talk about next time,
因为就像我们下次课会说到的那样
rates of depression are on the rise,
抑郁率呈上升趋势
rates of anxiety are on the rise,
焦虑率呈上升趋势
not just in this country, globally.
不只是在这个国家 是全球化的现象
It's literally global epidemic.
简直就是全球传染病
And to deal with it,
而为了应对它
more information will just not do.
更多的信息也并不够
Just not enough.
并不够
Here is Archibald MacLeish.
下面是Archibald MacLeish的话
He was a poet, was a Harvard professor,
他生前是一位诗人 是哈佛的教授
"What is wrong is not the great discoveries of science--
"错的不是科学的重大发现
information is always better than ignorance,
有信息永远比无知强
no matter what information or what ignorance.
不管是什么样信息和什么样无知
What is wrong is the belief behind the information,
错在于信息背后的信念
the belief that information will change the world.
认为信息会改变世界的信念
It won't."
但它不会"
Just adding it and filling up our containers with more and more stuff.
往我们的容器里增加 装上越来越多的东西
More and more information, more and more data.
越来越多的信息 越来越多的数据
It's just not enough.
还是不够
We need more than that.
我们需要更多
This class will take a humanistic approach.
本课程将采用一种人性的方法
Let me read you a quick excerpt by Abraham Maslow who talks about this approach,
我来给你们读一小段Abraham Maslow的话
"If one took a course or picked up a book on the psychology of learning,
"如果有人上了一门关于心理学学习的课
most of it,
或者看了一本这方面的书
in my opinion, would be beside the point -
大部分内容 在我看来 是与重点无关的
that is, beside the 'humanistic' point.
也就是 与人性无关
Most of it would present learning as the acquisition of associations,
大部分内容把学习展现为获得联想
of skills and capacities that are external and not intrinsic to the human character,
技能和能力 这些对于人的性格 人的个性
to the human personality, to the person himself."
人本身来说只是外在而并非本质的"
External refers to information.
外在是指信息
Internal refers to the transformation,
内在是指转变
the changing of the form.
形态的改变
And when we talk about transformation,
当我们谈到转变时
actually mean it quite literally--
实际上是非常字面的说法
changing of the form,
形态的改变
changing of the brain as we'll talk about.
大脑的改变 我们一会就谈到
We'll talk about meditation for instance.
比如我们会谈到冥想
We know our brain today can actually change through MRI studies since 1998.
1998年通过的核磁共振研究我们知道大脑可以被改变
A new concept came up which is Neurogenesis or Neuroplasticity,
一个新的概念叫做神经形成或者神经可塑性
meaning our brain actually changes and transforms.
是指我们的大脑实际上会改变和转变
It changes its form throughout our life.
在我们的一生中其形态都在改变
So I don't just mean it metaphorically,
所以我不只是在打比方
I also very often mean it literally.
我也经常指的是字面意义
Abraham Maslow continues,
继续Abraham Maslow的话
"Humanistic philosophy offers a new conception of learning,
"人性的哲学衍生出关于学习
of teaching, and of education.
教学和教育的新概念
Stated simply, such a concept holds that the function of education,
简单地说 这一概念认为教育的功能
the goal of education―
教育的目标
the human goal, the humanistic goal,
人的目标 人性的目标
the goal so far as human beings are concerned―
只要人还是被关注的目标
is ultimately the "self-actualization" of a person,
从根本上是一个人的自我实现
the becoming fully human,
完全成为一个人
the development of the fullest height that the human species can stand up to
达到人类或者是特定的某个个人
or that the particular individual can come to.
能达到的最高高度
In a less technical way,
通俗点讲
it is helping the person to become the best that he is able to become."
就是帮助一个人成为最好的自己"
And this was before the Ad came up for the army.
这些是军队的广告
That "Be all you can be."
"做最好的自己"
This is what the class is about.
这就是本课程所要讲的
It's the humanistic approach.
这就是人性的方法
It's about fulfilling our potential,
关于实现我们的潜能
chipping away those limitations.
凿掉那些束缚
Now to many of you this may sound naive, idealistic.
现在对于你们许多人这种方式似乎很天真 很理想主义
Naive it is not. Idealistic, it is.
并不天真 但理想主义
And we'll talk about and discuss the importance of idealism and maintaining idealism
我们会谈到和讨论理想主义和保持理想主义
if we are to introduce personal change,
的重要性 如果我们要介绍个人的改变
inter-personal change,
个人之间的改变
or community or society change.
或群体与社会的改变的话
This class is not about providing answers,
本课程不是提供
concerning the good life and happiness.
关于美好生活和幸福的答案的
It is about identifying the right questions.
是关于辨识正确的问题
"Ask and ye shall you receive", say the Scripture.
"问过之后便会有收获" 圣经如是说
This class is what I think education is all about,
本课程就是我认为的教育的宗旨
which is that the quest for information and transformation must begin with the question.
也就是对信息和转变的探索 必须由一个问题开始
Quest, question,
探索 问题
there is no coincidence that there is an etymological link between the two.
这两者在词源上有所关联并非巧合
In this class we'll be asking,
在本课程中 我们会问
you'll be asked many questions,
你们会被问许多问题
questions that as you'll see, create reality.
你们将会看到那些问题 创造了现实
We'll talk about it already next time.
我们下次会讲到
The importance of the questions you ask of yourselves first and foremost,
那些你首先向你自己
of your partner, of your students,
然后向你的搭档 学生
of your parents, of your employees in the future,
搭档 未来的雇员
teammates and so on.
和同事提出的问题的重要性
Questions make a difference.
问题十分重要
Peter Drucker, "The most common source of mistakes in management decisions
Peter Drucker说"在管理决策中最常见的
is the emphasis on finding the right answer rather than the right question."
错误来源是强调找到正确答案而非正确的问题"
Peter Drucker, considered the most important management scholar of 20th century,
Peter Drucker是20世纪最重要的管理学学者
just recently passed away,
最近刚刚去世
saying the biggest mistake is not asking the right questions.
说最大的错误是没有问正确的问题
As we'll see next time,
我们下次会看到
this is the biggest mistake in research potentially.
这也是在研究中潜在的最大的错误
This is the biggest mistake in application.
这也是在应用中最大的错误
Not asking the right questions as well,
没有问正确的问题
whether it's in managing organizations,
不论是在管理组织
whether it's managing our lives.
还是在管理我们的生活
Now.
现在
When I said that questions are important and answers matter less,
当我说问题重要而答案没那么重要时
I am not coming from a point of relativism.
我不是从相对论的观点来说的
I'm not a relativist.
我不是相对论者
I think they are ...
我认为他们...
To some questions definitive answers that are important to know.
对于某些问题 知道决定性的答案很重要
However, what I'm saying is that it's important,
但是 我所说的是当提到教育时
not less important to focus on questions when it comes to education.
关注问题很重要 而不是较不重要
The educator, Neil Postman once said,
教育家Neil Postman曾经说过
"The kids enter schools as question marks and they leave as periods."
"孩子进校时像问号而毕业时像句号"
My hope in this class is to bring up many more question marks than periods.
我的希望是本课程培养的问号要比句号多
Once again, it's about chipping away the excess stone because as kids,
再一次 这是关于凿掉多余的石头
we are always asking questions.
因为作为孩子 我们永远都在问问题
We are always curious.
我们永远都很好奇
Let me show you a quick excerpt from a video of one of my favorite psychologists,
我来放一段我最喜爱的心理学家之一的录影
actually the commedian, Seinfeld.
其实是喜剧演员宋飞
Here he is talking about...
他要讲的是...
We will watch a lot of excerpts throughout the semester.
我们这个学期会看很多录影
Talking about what we were like as kids.
如果像孩子一样我们会是怎样
See is this in your way
看看你们看得见不
"So, the first couple of years I made my own costumes which of course sucked:
"于是前两年 我自己做服装 当然不怎么样
the ghost, the hobo...
鬼啊 流浪汉啊...
Then, finally, the third year, begging the parents,
第三年我终于求了爸妈
I got the Superman Halloween costume.
我得到了超人的万圣节服装
Not surprisingly.
并不奇怪
Cardboard box, self-made top, mask included.
纸盒箱 自己做的上衣 还有面具
Remember the rubber band on the back of that mask?
还记得面具后面的橡皮筋不?
That was a quality item there, wasn't it?
那可是个质量不错的玩意 不是吗?
That was good for about 10 seconds
它可以坚持用10秒钟
before it snapped out of that cheap little staple they put it in there with.
之后就会从那个廉价订书钉里掉出来
You go to your first house:
你去了第一个人家
"Trick or..." Snap!" It broke.
"不给糖就..."啪嗒 橡皮筋断了
I don't believe it!"
简直不敢相信!
"Wait up you guys! I gotta fix it!
"你们等我一下! 我能修好它!
Hey wait up! Wait up!"
等我一下! 等我一下!"
Kids don't say "wait".
孩子们不说"等"
They say "wait up! Hey wait up!"
他们说"等我一下! 等我一下!"
Coz when you are little your life is up.
因为当你还小的时候 你的生活都在上面
Your future is up. Everything you want is up.
你的未来在上面 你所要的一切都在上面
"Wait up! Hold up! Shut up!
"等一下! 举起来! 闭嘴!"
Momma, clean up! Let me stay up!"
"妈妈 打扫一下! 让我晚点睡吧!"
Parents of course are just the opposite. Everything is down.
父母当然刚好相反 一切都在下面
"Just calm down! Slow down!
"冷静! 慢一点!
Calm down here! Sit down. Put that down!"
给我冷静! 坐下 把那个放下!"
So again this curiosity,
所以孩子们的这种好奇
this looking up,
这种寻找
this opening up is opposed to closing down that kids have.
这种开放的心态是与封闭相反的
This notion. This is what I hope will happen in this class.
我希望在本课程中会产生这种观念
The one real objective of education
教育的真正目的
is to leave a man in the condition of continually asking questions.
是让一个人可以连续发问
So here is a longitudinal study that was done by John Carter.
所以下面讲讲John Carter所作的纵向研究
John Carter, professor of leadership management of the business school across the river,
John Carter 河对面的商学院的领导管理学教授
came to Harvard in 1972,
1972年来到哈佛
joined the faculty and started to follow Harvard class,
做了老师并开始关注哈佛的课程
MBA class of 1973 and followed them through 20 years.
从1973年起一直关注了20年MBA课程
And what he was interested in was to find all the information he could about this class.
他想尽可能收集所有关于这门课的信息
What he found 20 years later,
20年后 90年代初当这个研究结束时
early 90s when this study ended was these students were extremely successful,
他发现这些学生都极其成功
Or ex-students were extremely successful, students were extremely successful,
以前的学生都极其成功 学生们都极其成功
very wealthy, having a lot of impact,
非常有钱 有很大的影响力
whether it's on the organizations, on the community.
不论是在组织上 还是社会上
They did extremely well.
他们都做得极其好
But within the large group of highly successful Harvard MBAs,
但是在这群极其成功的哈佛MBA里
he found a small group that was extraordinarily successful,
他发现有一小部分人是格外成功的
more successful than the rest of group,
比其它人要更成功
whether in terms of income,
无论是在收入上
whether in terms of impact,
还是在影响力上
whether in terms of overall quality of life.
抑或是在总体生活质量上
Extraordinarily successful.
格外的成功
What he wanted to identify was why--
他想弄明白其中的原因
what distinguishes this small group from the rest of the pack:
这一小部分人和其他人有何区别
very successful, but not quite as successful as that small group.
其他人也非常成功 但没有那一小组人那么成功
And he found only two things.
他只找出了两件事
It was not their IQs that made no difference whatsoever to their long-term success.
不是他们的智商对他们长期成功的因素没有影响
It was not where they came from, pre-MBA,
不是他们在念MBA之前的出身
what they did had nothing to do with it.
他们做的事和这一点关系都没有
Two and two things along mattered in terms of determining
只有两件事会决定谁会成为格外成功的人
who will be the extraordinarily successful and the rest:
和其余的人上有关系
the first thing was the extraordinarily successful groups really believe in themselves.
第一是那部分人真的相信自己
They thought they could do well.
他们认为自己能做好
They were driven.
他们有目的
They were motivated.
他们有动力
And we'll talk about it in future lecture as belief in self-fulfilling prophecies.
我们会在下一次课讲到自我实现的预言
They thought "I'm going to make it.
他们认为"我会做到
I'm going to succeed."
我会成功"
That's the first thing.
这是第一件事
The sense of the confidence.
自信
The second thing that he found was this group,
他发现的第二件事是 这部分人
they were always asking questions,
一直在问问题
--always asking questions,
一直问问题
initially of their boss,
最初是问他们的老板
later of their employees,
后来是问他们的雇员
of their partners, children, parents, friends.
他们的搭档 孩子 父母 朋友
They were always asking question.
他们一直在问问题
They were always at the state of curiosity.
他们一直处于好奇的状态
Always looking up, opening up,
一直在寻找 有开放的心态
wanting to understand the world the more.
想要更加了解世界
They didn't say "Now I have my MBA.
他们没有说"我现在有了MBA学位
That's it. I know enough.
就行了 我知道的够多了"
" They were life-long learners.
他们是终身学习者
They were always asking questions.
他们一直在问问题
These two distinguishing characteristics
这两个区别性的特质
account for the difference between the extraordinarily successful and those who were successful.
导致了格外成功和成功的人之间的差别
The question that has guided me whether it's in writing the book,
那个指引了我的问题 不论是写书
whether it's in creating this class,
还是开设这门课程
whether it's first and foremost my personal life is what I call "the question of the question",
还是被我所称的"问题的问题"
which is "how can we help ourselves and others,
就是"我们如何能帮助自己和他人
individuals, communities and society become happier?"
个人 群体和社会变得更幸福?"
Note that it is not about helping ourselves and others become happy.
注意这不是关于帮助我们自己和他人变得幸福
It is about becoming happier.
而是关于变得更幸福
Why? Because many people ask me,
为什么? 因为很多人问我
"So Tal, are you happy?"
"那么Tal 你幸福吗?"
And I can't really answer that question.
我真的不能回答那个问题
I don't know what it means.
我不知道那是什么意思
How do I determine whether or not I am happy?
我如何判断自己是否幸福?
Is it compared to someone else?
是和别人比较?
Is there a certain point beyond which I become happy?
是不是存在一个点 超过之后就变幸福了?
Happiness is not a binary either-or, zero-one--
幸福不是二进制的非此即彼 0或1
either I'm happy or I'm unhappy.
要么幸福要么不幸福
Happiness resides on a continuum.
幸福存在于一个连续统一体
So my answer to this question-- "am I happy?"
所以我对这个问题的回答-- "我幸福吗?"
is today I'm happier than I was 15 years ago when I started focusing on this pursuit.
我今天是否比我15年前刚开始关注幸福时更幸福
15 years from now I certainly hope to be happier than I am today.
15年后我当然希望自己能比今天幸福
Happiness is lifelong pursuit.
幸福是终身的追求
Hopefully this class is part of that pursuit,
希望本课程是这种追求的一部分
but just part.
但只是一部分
You'll not be happy at the end of class.
你们不会在课结束时幸福
Hopefully you'll be happier.
希望你们能比现在幸福
Cos many people sit here during the lectures on self-esteem, for example,
因为很多人坐在这听有关自尊的讲座时 比如
or when we talk explicitly about happiness,
或者当我们明确地讨论幸福时
they say, "Wait. Do I have self-esteem?"--
他们说 "等等 我的自尊心强吗?"
Thinking to themselves.
他们自己想到
"Do I have high self-esteem or low self-esteem?" Irrelevant.
"我的自尊是较强的还是较弱的?"
Impossible to answer also.
这也是没有意义 无法回答的
The question is "how can I improve my self-esteem,
问题是"我如何能提高我的自尊
my healthy self-esteem,
我健康的自尊
not narcissism of course?
而当然不是自恋?
How can I become happier?"
我怎样才能变得幸福?"
That's an important question.
那是一个重要的问题
And this is the question of questions.
这是问题的问题
This class is not a survey of positive psychology.
本课程不是一个积极心理学的概论
If you want a survey on positive psychology,
如果你想要关于积极心理学的概论
I can recommend some excellent textbooks
我可以推荐一些很不错的课本
whether it's by Lopez (Shane J. Lopez) or by Peterson (Chris Peterson).
Lopez或是Peterson的书
Great textbooks. There is also The Handbook of Positive Psychology
很不错的课本 还有一本积极心理学手册
which is a huge book with most what you want to know about this field.
一本很厚的书 里面有这个领域里大多数你想知道的内容
You can also use it in self-defense.
你也可以用它自卫
Very useful in that respect.
自卫非常管用
But a wonderful book, very well-written,
但是本很棒的书 写得非常好
very accessible in the spirit of positive psychology.
让人很容易理解积极心理学
But this is not that.
但这里讲的不是那些
This is not a survey of positive psychology.
不是积极心理学概论
What it is is a selective exploration of the question of the questions.
而是对"问题中的问题"的选择性探索
In that way, it is eclectic.
从那个角度讲 它是折衷的
My background is in psychology and philosophy.
我的背景是心理学和哲学
I studies organizational behavior.
我学了组织行为学
I worked as a consultant in business for a few years.
我做过几年商业顾问
Still do some work there.
仍然还做一些这方面的工作
I worked in the field of education,
我在教育领域工作过
doing a lot of work in field of education.
在教育领域内做过很多工作
And I take from all these areas.
我从所有这些领域中吸取内容
I also draw on not just from positive psychology.
我还不只是从积极心理学中吸取内容
I draw on clinical psychology in this class.
我把临床心理学的内容融入这个课程中
I draw on cognitive psychology,
我融入了认知心理学
social psychology and so on.
社会心理学等等内容
It's an eclectic class.
这是一个折衷的课程
Because my question,
因为我的问题
my guiding question was "what would contribute to happiness?"
我的引导性问题是"什么会对幸福有贡献?"
And if something within psychopathology I thought could contribute to our wellbeing,
如果我认为精神病理学的内容
I took that and used that.
能对我们的幸福有贡献 我会吸取并利用之
And if something from the field of consulting in organizational behavior could contribute,
而如果一些有关组织行为学的咨询领域的东西有用
that became part of the class,
那也会成为本课程的一部分
as much as I could fit in of course in one semester.
只要能在一个学期内讲完
So the class is eclectic.
所以本课程是折衷的
The class is not cross-cultural.
本课程不是跨文化交流
I will bring in ideas from eastern thoughts.
我会引进一些东方思想的观点
I lived in Asia for a few years.
我在亚洲住过几年
I worked there.
我在那工作
Studied and continue to study the eastern philosophies and psychologies.
持续研究东方哲学和心理学
But my train primarily is in western psychology.
但我的专业主要是在西方心理学上
And the focus of the class will be that.
而课程的重点将会是西方心理学
However that doesn't mean
但是那并不意味着
that positive psychology doesn't apply to people from different places in the world.
积极心理学不适用于世界上其他地方的人
There was recently a meeting between senior scientists,
最近有一场高资历科学家之间的会议
psychologists from the west,
来自西方的心理学家
people like Paul Ekman, Richard Davidson-
像Paul Ekman和Richard Davidson
some of the most important minds in the field of psychology
这些在心理学领域内最重要的人物
meeting with the Dalai Lama and some of his monks.
和达赖喇嘛还有他的一些僧侣进行会谈
They were talking about the future of psychology, about the research,
他们谈论了心理学的未来 研究
and how can you research meditation and so on.
还有如何研究冥想等等
And one of the things they were talking a lot about is the cross-cultural differences.
而他们谈论较多的话题之一就是文化差异
And when that came up,
当提到这个问题时
the Dalai Lama suddenly seemed uneasy.
达赖喇嘛突然好像很不舒服
And when Daniel Goleman who was writting about this whole event
当记录整个会议的Daniel Goleman
and it was held in India asked him what's wrong,
会议是在印度开的 问他怎么了
Dalai Lama said that he was not comfortable with talking and emphasizing so much cultural differences.
他说他不是因为谈到并强调文化差异而不舒服
You can say many things about Dalai Lama.
对达赖喇嘛你可以有很多评价
One thing you cannot say about him is that he's culturally insensitive,
但你不能说他在文化方面不敏感
arguably one of the most sensitive people alive.
他可以说是还在世的最敏感的人之一
And yet he said  we are focusing too much on cultural differences
然而他说 我们对文化差异的关注太多了
and he added not because there are no cultural differences.
他补充道不是因为没有文化差异
Of course there are and they are important.
当然有而且很重要
But there are many more similarities than differences.
但文化共同性要比差异多
And we shouldn't ignore those similarities.
而我们不应该无视这些共同性
Daniel Goleman about the Dalai Lama,
Daniel Goleman如此评价达赖喇嘛
"We were a little bit surprised by the Dalai Lama's seeming resistance
"我们有点惊讶于达赖喇嘛这种表面上的
to the notion of cultural differences.
对文化差异概念的抵触"
So I am willing to introduce these ideas but A,
所以我想介绍这些观点 但是首先
because it's not my training and people
因为这不是我的专业
who are focusing on cultural differences will do a much better job than I do;
研究文化差异的人会比我做得更好
and second, because what I hope to look into is the universal,
其次 因为我所希望研究的是普遍事物
things are common across cultures.
不同文化中普遍的东西
So we'll study research in this area.
所以我们会在这方面进行研究
But even more than that,
但不只是这样
we'll become even more particular than just talking about psychology in this part of the world.
我们的讨论比这部分心理学更具体
We'll study yourselves.
我们将会研究你们自己
We are going to go that particular.
我们会如此具体
Now why? When I put this class together,
为什么? 当我开这门课程时
I didn't think to myself,
我自己没想过
"Ok, so what are the things that I need to introduce
"好的 我需要介绍些什么东西
in order to please the participants in the class, the students?"
以便能取悦课程的参与者 这些学生呢?"
That's not what I thought.
那不是我所想的
What I thought about was "what was the class that I would have wanted to take as an undergraduate here?
我所想的是"如果我是个本科生 会想上什么课?
What would help me become happier if I were sitting there?"
如果我坐在这 什么能让我更幸福?"
In other words, thinking from my perspective from very personal perspective.
换言之 从我的观点 从非常个人的观点出发
In this class I am going to encourage you.
在我们的课上 我会鼓励你们
Of course you'll look at research and read research about other people,
当然你们可以看和阅读关于别人的研究
about large sample sizes.
有大量的样本
But I'm going to encourage you more than anything to look inside yourselves.
但最主要的 我会鼓励你们去看自己的内心
To study yourselves.
去研究自己
Whether it's through response papers that will be due weekly starting in 2 weeks;
无论是通过两周后开始的每周一次的课后论文
whether it's in your final project that will be a presentation
还是你们最后的演示作业 你们不用做演示
that you won't have to give but you'll have to write out--
但要写出来 一个关于你最感兴趣的话题
a presentation about your favorite topic or the topic that matters most to you;
或者对你来说最重要的话题的演示
whether it's in sections that you'll be talking about how can I apply these ideas to my life.
还是关于如何能把这些观点应用于我的生活
The time-ins are about thinking about how can I take in the ideas and use them.
"练习时间"是关于如何接受和利用一些观点
It's about studying ourselves.
是关于研究我们自己
Because as Carl Rogers says,
因为正如Carl Rogers所说
"What is most personal is most general."
"越是个人的东西越普遍"
And as Maslow adds,
正如Maslow所补充
"We must remember that knowledge of one's own deep nature
"我们必须记住对一个人深层本性的认识
is also simultaneously knowledge of human nature in general."
同时也是对普遍人类本性的认识"
When we understand ourselves better,
当我们更了解自己时
when we identify ourselves,
当我们认识到自己时
we are better able to identify with others.
我们就更能认识他人
In fact, this is in many ways the source of empathy, of the healthy empathy.
事实上 从许多方面说这是有益移情的来源
And there are some studies showing that people who know themselves,
有些研究表明了解自己的人
who study themselves, who are self-reflective,
研究自己的人 反思自己的人
display less egregious behavior,
对别人做出过分的行为
less immoral behavior toward others.
不道德的行为会相对较少
Behavior that would fall under say, racism.
那种比如说种族歧视的行为
And it's counter-intuitive to some extent.
在一定程度上这是反直觉的
"Wait. Don't you first need to study the other
"等等 你难道不要首先研究别人
so that you can be more sensitive to others?"
才能对别人更敏感吗?"
Yes, that too.
是的 那也需要
But it's not enough.
不过还不够
It is important to also study ourselves,
研究我们自己也很重要
because when we see our deep nature,
因为当我们看到自己的深层本性时
what we encounter there is part of the universal nature,
我们看到的是部分普遍的本性
the similarities among us all,
我们所有人之间的共性
regardless of where we are from.
不管我们来自哪里
And this was what Dalai Lama was talking about:
而这就是达赖喇嘛所说的
not stop cross-cultural.
不是阻止跨文化研究
Do it. Important.
去做吧 很重要
But at the same time, not ignore the self.
但同时 不要忽视自己
Not ignore the universal within each one of us.
不要忽视我们每一个人身上的普遍性
C.S. Lewis, "There is one thing and only one in the whole universe
C.S. Lewis说 "整个宇宙中有且只有一件
which we know about that we could learn from external observation.
我们知道我们可以从外部观察中学习到的事
That one thing is ourselves.
那就是我们自己
We have, so to speak, inside information;
我们有 可以说是 内在的信息
we are in the know."
我们是知道的"
Now there are of course biases when we study ourselves
当我们研究自己时当然会有偏颇
which is why it's not enough to just study the self.
这就是为什么只研究自己是不够的
It's important to counter it,
要克服这个问题
to add to it, academic work, studying others.
把学术工作 研究他人融入进去很重要
That's why we'll do some research or study research as well as do some search--
那就是为什么我们除了探究我们的内心外
searching inside us.
也会做一些研究或调查研究
Both are important.
两者并重
We shouldn't, just because there are biases and mistakes that potentially can be made,
我们不应该 只是因为会有潜在的偏颇和错误
it doesn't mean we need to throw out the baby with the bath water
这并不意味着我们要因噎废食
and stop studying ourselves.
停止探究自己
So we'll do that or rather you'll do that probably more than any other class on campus.
所以我们会 更准确地说是你们会这样做 比学校里的其他课程做得要多
Finally this may be news to you,
最后这个可能对你们来说有些新
but this is not English 10A or Math 55,
但这不是10A号英语课和55号数学课 就是说
meaning you'll not have to read as much as you will read for 10A or for a history class,
你不用像10A号课或者历史课那样做大量的阅读
and this class is not as difficult as Math 55 so you rest.
也不像55号数学课一样难 所以你们可以轻松些
I'm sure there are some people here who took the class.
我相信这有些人上过这门课
This class at the same time is about rigorous fun.
本课程同时是一种严格的乐趣
Fun...because it's fun to study ourselves.
乐趣...因为研究我们自己很有意思
Sometimes it hurts and sometimes we see things that we may not like,
有时会让我们受伤 有时我们看到一些我们不愿意看到的东西
but overall it's fun.
但总的来说还是有趣的
It's interesting.
很有意思
And at the same time it's rigorous, based on research.
同时又是严格的 以研究为基础
Now many of the ideas that you'll encounter in this class are very simple,
你们将在本课程中遇到的许多观点都很简单
very accessible.
很容易理解
Common sense.
常识
However they are simple, not simplistic.
但它们是简单 不是过分简单化
And here is the difference.
这两者是有区别的
Oliver Wendell Holmes--
Oliver Wendell Holmes
this court is attributed to him,
这个报告厅就是他捐建的
not 100% sure it's his-- said,
但不能完全确定是他所有的--说过
"I would not give a fig for the simplicity on this side of complexity,
"我不会认为与复杂性一致的简单性是微不足道的
but I would give my life for the simplicity on the other side of complexity."
但我会把一生用来研究与复杂性相对的简单性"
What Holmes means here is that he doesn't care about just simplicity,
Homles这里的意思是他关心的不只是简单性
easy, off-the-cuff, whimsical ideas.
简单的 随意的 难以预料的想法
What he does care about though is the simplicity that comes after.
而他所关心的是之后的简单性
We have chewed the idea,
我们深思了这个观点
after we have digested it,
在我们吸收了它之后
after we have thought about it.
在我们考虑过它之后
Ideas that have been worked on.
那些我们所研究的观点
And if on the other side of complexity we can read simplicity and common sense,
而如果与复杂性相反 我们能看出简单性和常识
that's great.
那就很好
That's what he's interested in.
那是他所感兴趣的
That is also positive psychology researchers
那也是我们整个学期要讨论的
that we'll discuss throughout the semester are interested in.
积极心理学研究者所感兴趣的
The simplicity on the other side of complexity.
与复杂性相对的简单性
And there is a very big difference between these two simplicities,
这两种简单性之间有很大的区别
even though on the face of it,
尽管乍看起来
they may at times look similar.
他们有时也许是相似的
What this class requires is a very different kind of effort.
本课程需要的是一种非常不同的努力
A very different kind of effort to other class.
与别的课程非常不同的努力
Again it doesn't require the effort that you'll need in 55 or in English 10A.
它不需要你像55号课和10A号英语课那样的努力
The kind of effort that it does require is the effort of application,
它所需要的努力是一种应用的努力
of applying into your life,
努力把它应用到你的生活里
of introducing behavioral actual change to your life.
努力把行为的实际改变带入你的生活
And before we go into some of the technicalities of the class such as the syllabus,
在我们开始讲本课程的一些细节像教学大纲之前
I want to end with a story about Peter Drucker.
我想先讲一个关于Peter Drucker的故事
Peter Drucker, who I quoted earlier,
Peter Drucker 我之前引用过他的话
father of study of management in modern times.
是现代管理学研究之父
Peter Drucker lived to the grand old age of 94,
Peter Drucker享年94岁
passed away just a couple of years ago.
是几年前过世的
Toward the end of his life while he was still 100% lucid,
在他生命的最后当他头脑还百分百清醒时
it was more difficult for him to be mobile and to go into organizations.
活动和参加组织活动对他来说更加困难了
So what he did was invite people who wanted consulting from him,
于是他邀请想咨询他问题的人
wanted to learn from him to come to his home.
想跟他学习的人来他家
And he had Presidents,
有国家总统
Premier Ministers of countries.
总理
He had CEOs of Fortune 500 companies coming spend the weekend with him.
财富500强公司的CEO和他一起过周末
And on Friday, this was how we started with every session,
而在星期五 每一次聚会都是这样开始的
with every world leader,
对每一个世界级领袖
whether in business, whether in non-for-profit, whether in politics.
无论是商界的 非盈利机构的 还是政界的
He would say to them the following,
他都会对他们说如下的一番话
"on Monday I don't want you to call me up and tell me how wonderful it was,
"星期一我不想听到你们说这有多美好"
"-- meaning how wonderful the weekend was,
意思是这个周末有多美好
"on Monday I want you to call me up
"星期一我想听到你们跟我说
and tell me what you are doing differently."
你们做了些什么改变"
At the end of the semester or at the end of the lecture,
在这学期结束后或者在这个讲座结束后
if you enjoyed it,
如果你们喜欢它
by all means tell me that you enjoyed it, that you had fun.
务必告诉我你们喜欢 你们获得了乐趣
But more important, it is what you are doing differently,
但更重要的是你们所做的改变是什么
how this has an impact on your life and that takes effort.
这对你们的生活有怎样的影响 而那需要我们的努力
We are going to spend a whole week talking just about change,
我们将用一周的时间讲改变
nothing directly related to positive psychology.
和积极心理学一点直接的关系也没有
Just about change.
只是讲改变
Because it is so difficult to change.
因为改变是那么难
Because we know most organizational change fails,
因为我们知道大多数组织上的改变都失败了
because we know more individual change fails.
因为我们知道更多的个人改变失败了
Unless we introduce behavioral change along with our cognitive and emotional change.
除非我们在引入行为上的改变的同时 引入认知上和情绪上的改变
Affect and cognition is not enough; behavior has to be there as well.
影响和认知还不够 还要有行为
What you are doing differently.
你所做的改变
To do things differently very often takes courage.
经常用不同的方式做事需要勇气
Some of your response papers that you'll hand in--
一些你们要交上来的课后论文
none of them are graded; they are all just graded "pass/failed"--
都不会被打分 都只会有"及格和不及格"
you'll have to hand them in and then you'll pass.
你们必须交论文 然后你们就及格了
But some of them may be the most difficult papers that you've written here.
但一些也许是你所写过的最困难的论文
For some they'll be the easiest.
有一些会是最简单的
And things will just flow out.
很自然地就能写出来
That's about introducing change.
那就是关于引入改变
That's about reflecting.
那就是关于反思
That's about taking time-in.
那就是关于花时间接受
That's about chipping away the excess stone.
那就是关于凿掉多余的石头
And it can only be done through this kind of effort.
而这只能通过这种努力而实现
So if you really want class to make a difference in your life, it's up to you.
所以如果你真的想通过这门课改变生活 一切取决于你
I'm going to introduce to you the material.
我将会给你们介绍材料
I'm going to introduce to you this wonderful new field of positive psychology.
我将会给你们介绍这个积极心理学的精彩新领域
what is up to you is to then take it and apply it.
而取决于你们的就是接受并应用它
I want to talk a little about the syllabus and the requirements.
我想谈一下教学大纲及要求
And I'll give you a little time for questions.
我会给你们一点时间去问问题
But before I do that,
但在这之前
I would also like to welcome--
我也想对
I know that some of you are watching this from home,
我知道你们中的有些人正在家里看这堂课
to the extension school students,
对进修学校的同学们表示欢迎
it's wonderful to have you here.
很高兴你们能听我的课
Do come and visit once a while.
有空过来看看
And you'll be working with obviously part of this class,
而你们将显然参与到我们的课程中来
but also with Deb Levy who is the,
但也可以找Deb Levy
they had teaching fellow for the extension school.
他是进修学校的助教
They had teaching fellow for the FAS class is Sean Achor
Sean Achor是文理学院的助教
and I'd like just to invite him for just a few words,
我想请他来说几句话
just to introduce himself to you.
向你们做个自我介绍
And you'll be introduced to other TFs we have.
而你们会被介绍给我们的其他助教
We have an amazing team this year.
我们今年有支很棒的团队
This is Sean.
这就是Sean
Sean:Hey good morning.
嘿 上午好
Can you guys hear me?
能听到我吗?
Can you hear me now? Great.
现在能听得到吗? 很好
This is absolutely honored to be back teaching positive psychology again.
能回来再次为积极心理学做助教非常荣幸
Tal is too humble.
Tal太谦虚了
This is not only extraordinary that he is sharing his time with us,
很荣幸他能给我们上课
but he's actually moved here back,
他还把家搬来了
moved his family back from Israel for the entire semester,--
把家从以色列搬到这一整个学期
his wife and his two little children just so he can teach this class with us.
包括他的妻子和他的两个孩子 只是为了能和我们一起教这门课
And this is absolutely an extraordinary opportunity for us to share this moment with them.
对我们来说能和他们一起共事是个极好的机会
And I'm really excited about it.
我真的很激动
Last time we taught this class,
上一次我们教这门课时
we did a survey to find out what type of people were sitting in this room--
我们做了一个调查 看看坐在这上课的都是什么类型的人
they are just like yourselves--
他们就像你们一样
and find out why you'll be taking this class.
看看为什么你们会上这门课
Coz the comment that we get so often about this class
因为我们得到的关于这门课的评价常常是
is why would Harvard students possibly be unhappy?
为什么哈佛的学生会不幸福?
what do they have to be unhappy about?
他们有什么可不快乐的?
They thought everyone who'd be taking this class would be taking it
他们认为每个上这门课的人会上这门课
because they are already really happy
是因为他们已经很幸福了
and they want to study about how amazing they are.
他们想研究自己到底有多棒
And they'd like to learn things that they can tell the roommates so clearly that (?) themselves.
他们想学一些能明白地告诉室友他们得意的东西
But it turns out actually over a third of people who took this class last year took the class
但是结果是去年有超过三分之一的人
because they felt depressed.
选这门课是因为他们感觉抑郁
And they were trying to learn about the research about positive psychology.
他们想学习积极心理学
And another third because they wanted to learn about optimism.
还有三分之一是因为他们想学会乐观
Another third did it for completely different reasons.
另外三分之一的原因则完全不同
I think. Additional third this year did it because Tal was on the Jon Stewart Daily Show.
我想 今年还有三分之一的人选这门课是因为
I am absolutely thrilled about this class.
Tal上了Jon Stewart的Daily Show 我很喜欢这门课
The syllabus which Tal is about to tell you about is..
Tal要告诉你们的教学大纲是...
Actually we learned a couple of other things about you guys.
其实我们了解你们的一些其他事
Did you know that of people who take positive psychology,
你知不知道选了积极心理学的人中
75% of you are officers of club,
有75%的人是俱乐部的干部
35% of you are the highest ranking officers of club,
35%是俱乐部的高层干部
which means that you think there are about 2000 clubs at Harvard,
这意味着 你认为哈佛有大约2000个俱乐部
you are in club of three,
你在一个只有3个人的俱乐部里
and you happen to be the president.
又恰好是主席
We learned other reasons why you are not happy.
我们了解到你们不快乐的其他原因
we learned that the average number of romantic relationships
我们了解到上积极心理学课的人
for people to take positive psychology in 4 years is between zero and one.
在4年里恋爱次数的平均数在0到1之间
Zero and one.
0到1之间
(Tal: No! I don't believe it.)
不! 我不信
Don't leave.
不要走
- But that was before taking positive psychology class. - That was before taking the class.
- 但那是在上积极心理学课之前 - 是在上课之前
We are going to test you afterwards.
我们之后会调查一下你们
The average number of sexual partners is between zero and .5.
性伴侣数目的平均数是在0到0.5之间
I have no idea what .5 sexual partners is.
我实在不知道0.5个性伴侣是什么
This class is going to be amazing.
这门课程将会很棒
It was amazing in the past and Tal we actually have extraordinary teaching staff here with us.
它过去就很棒 而且我们有一个很出色的教学团队
It's a large teaching staff.
很大的教学团队
And Tal has actually already given us home works
Tal实际上已经给我们布置了作业
so the teachers are going to be learning not only the material you are doing
所以老师们不仅要学你们学的那些材料
and talk you about which the experts (?),
和你们讨论专业的内容
but learning how to be better teachers.
还要学习如何成为更好的老师
He's given us books to read.
他给了我们要读的书
He's actually given us assignment.
他事实上给我们布置了任务
It's a big extraordinary class in that sense.
从那个意义上说这是个很特别的课程
In terms of the syllabus, it's going to be online.
至于教学大纲 网上会有
Tal just described now we've decided to go green,
Tal说现在我们决定要环保
so no trees are in making of this class except the large auditorium made of wood.
所以这门课程中不能使用树木制品 除了这个木制的大礼堂
Sections-- we are going to try sections online next weekend.
我们下周会在网上分组
So we are going to get the numbers on Wednesday.
所以我们星期三会知道有多少分组
On following weekend we will be doing sectioning
下个周末我们会做分组任务
that gives you a very short of turnaround time.
给你们的周转时间就非常少了
But that way you can give me Monday to change your section if you need to,
如果需要的话 你们可以在周一换组
which I hope you won't.
虽然我不希望你们改
And sections will start the following week.
分组会在下一个星期开始
Thank you very much. If you have any questions, send me an email.
非常谢谢 如果还有什么问题 给我发邮件
Ok, so...
好的 那么...
I think I don't need to explain to you
我想我不需要跟你们解释
why there is one lecture in the semester that I don't teach and Sean will teach it.
为什么这学期有一节课不是我教而是Sean教的
And that is the lecture on humor.
而那节是讲幽默的
Figure out why yourselves.
你们自己想想为什么
I do think you'll have to walk and talk if you are teaching something.
我确实认为如果你想教什么你就必须擅长
The syllabus.
教学大纲
The class, is to introduce you to my thinking about the class,
本课程 是向你介绍我关于这门课程的想法的
is what I call it,
是我所谓的
integrated class.
整体的课程
What that means is that integrated vertically as well as horizontally.
就是指纵向的整体和横向的整体
Vertically means that every class connected to the next class
纵向意味着每一节课都和下一节课有关系
is connected to every class throughout the semester around a spiral.
和整个学期内的每一节课都有关系 呈一个螺旋状
So what we'll talk about next week,
所以我们下周所讲的内容
we'll revisit it again in lesson 7,
我们将在第7课 第17课和第24课里
lesson 17 and lesson 24.
再回顾一遍
Everything is interconnected on the higher level on a spiral--
所有内容在一个更高的水平上呈螺旋状互相联系
in other words will lead to deep understanding and hopefully assimilation of the material.
换言之 会带来深刻的理解和我所希望的对材料的吸收
So it's vertically interconnected.
所以是纵向相互联系的
It's also horizontally interconnected.
同样也是横向相互联系的
That means every part of the class reinforces and influences the other part.
就是说课程中的每一部分都强调并影响另一部分
The lectures, not enough, you'll get a lot more in sections.
上课还不够 你们在分组作业里面将收获更多
Sections are mandatory.
分组作业是强制的
You'll do a lot of work in your sections,
你们要在你们的分组里做大量
very much related to your response papers
和你的课后论文相关的工作
that many student claim the most important part of the class.
许多学生说这是本课程最重要的一部分
Because that's where you get the time-in.
因为这样你们才有了练习时间
That's when you really get to chip away.
这是你真正开始凿掉的时候
Very much connected to the final project.
和期末的大作业有很大的关系
The final project is a presentation that you'll write out.
期末作业是一个演示稿
You don't actually give it but give it to a couple of friends just to get feedback.
你们不用真的做演示 但要向几个朋友演示以获得反馈
Not graded on that part.
那部分不计分
The final project is graded as a final paper,
期末作业是以期末论文计分的
but just what you hand in,
但只是你们交上来的
what you submit.
你们提交的那份
And the reason why there is a final paper because the best way which is like a presentation,
为什么写期末论文 是因为像演示那样的最好的方式
because the best way to learn is to teach.
因为最好的学习方式是教
And you'll be teaching these materials to other people --
你们将把这些材料教给别人
any material that you are interested in in your presentation.
任何在你的陈述中你所感兴趣的内容
So the readings,
那么阅读
very much connected and take you to the next level of understanding and assimilation.
非常有关系 会把你们带到理解和吸收的另一个水平高度
So any questions before I finish up? Any question from you?
在我讲完之前有问题吗? 你们有什么要问的吗?
Alright. So let me just say-- one second finishing words.
好了 那就让我说 最后一秒钟结束语
I am very excited to be back here.
对于能回到这里我感到非常激动
My families are very excited to be back here.
我的家人对于回到这里也很激动
Looking forward to a meaningful, pleasurable,
期望能和你们共度一个有意义的 愉快的
enjoyable and happier semester with you.
令人享受的和更加幸福的学期
Thank you.
谢谢